2

Terminology

The New Testament writers give a clear picture of the nature and activity of demons, but the key to understanding these areas is an accurate explanation of the terminology they used. Unfortunately, there are weaknesses in the way different English versions have translated certain expressions from the original Greek text, which have obscured the meaning for English readers. It is necessary, therefore, to begin by examining the main words used in the Greek.

Three expressions are used to describe the evil spirit beings who are some of Satan’s main agents in his warfare against humanity. First, demon (Greek, daimonion). This is the neuter singular of the adjective daimonios, which is derived from the noun daimon. Thus the adjective daimonios indicates some connection with a daimon. Although daimonion is adjectival in form, it is used regularly as a noun. It is, in fact, an adjective that has become a noun. We can illustrate this from a contemporary example in English. Green is another adjective that has become a noun, describing a person concerned about protecting the environment. Hence we now talk of the “greens.”

In English the important distinction between daimon and daimonion is obliterated by the fact that both words are normally translated by one and the same English word: demon. Throughout this book, however, wherever it is necessary to preserve the distinction, we will continue to use the Greek words transliterated into English and italicised – that is, daimon and daimonion. We will form the plural in English simply by adding s, although this is not the correct way to form the plural in Greek.

The reference to the original Greek indicates that there are two distinct entities: daimon, which is primary, and daimonion, which is derivative. (This has an important bearing on the nature of demons, to which we will return in chapter 11, “What Are Demons?”) The derivative form, daimonion, occurs about sixty times in the gospels, Acts and Revelation. In other words, it represents an important New Testament concept. In the best texts, daimon occurs only once – in Matthew 8:31, where it is apparently used with the same meaning as daimonion. But this is not a normal use.

The second expression used in the New Testament to describe an evil spirit is unclean spirit, used about twenty times in Luke, Acts and Revelation.

The third expression, evil spirit, is used six times in Luke and Acts.

In Luke 4:33 two of these expressions are combined as the writer speaks of “a spirit of an unclean demon” (daimonion).

Altogether it seems that all three expressions are used interchangeably. “Demons” are “unclean spirits” and also “evil spirits.”

The original King James Version regularly translates daimonion as “devil.” This has led to endless confusion. The English word devil is actually derived from the Greek word diabolos, which has no direct relationship with daimonion. Diabolos means “slanderer.” In all but three occurrences in the New Testament, it is a title of Satan himself. In this sense it is used only in the singular form. There are many demons but only one devil.

Satan is given this title because his primary activity is to slander – that is, to defame a person’s character. First and foremost, Satan defames the character of God Himself. He did this in the Garden of Eden, when he suggested to Adam and Eve that God was not treating them fairly by withholding from them the knowledge of good and evil. Second, Satan defames the character of all those who in any way represent God. This is his primary weapon against the servants of God. All the main translations subsequent to the kjv have observed the distinction between diabolos and daimonion, and have translated diabolos as “devil” and daimonion as “demon.”

Unfortunately, there is another area of confusion that has not been cleared up in some of the modern translations. The Greek noun daimon gives rise to a verb daimonizo, which occurs about twelve times in the New Testament. The obvious English equivalent of this verb is demonize, which the Collins English Dictionary defines as “to subject to demonic influence.” In the New Testament this verb occurs only in the passive form: “to be demonized.” In the original kjv, it is translated regularly as “to be possessed of [or with] a devil or devils.” Most modern versions have correctly changed devil to demon, but incorrectly retain the form to be possessed.

The problem with this form is that, to English ears, the word possess immediately suggests ownership. To be “possessed” – by a devil or demon – implies that a person is “owned” by a devil or demon. But there is no basis for this in the Greek word daimonizo, which conveys no suggestion of ownership, but means merely “to subject to demonic influence.”

Obviously the form of words we use is of vital importance. It is one thing to say to a person, “You are subject to demonic influence.” It is quite another to say, “You are possessed by a demon,” or, worse still, to say, “You are possessed by the devil.”

Let me say emphatically that there is nothing in the verb daimonizo to imply possession. Personally I believe that every born-again Christian sincerely seeking to live for Christ belongs to Christ and is owned by Him. It is monstrous to suggest that such a person belongs to the devil or is owned by the devil.

On the other hand, I know on the basis of my own experience, and of ministering to thousands of others, that a born-again Christian can be subject to demonic influences. Such a Christian undoubtedly belongs to Christ, yet there are areas of his or her personality that have not yet come under the control of the Holy Spirit. It is these areas that may still be subject to demonic influence.

Throughout the rest of this book, then, I will for the most part speak of such people as those who are “demonized.”

The Greek verb that usually describes the action of getting rid of a demon is ekballo, normally translated “to drive out,” but in the kjv regularly translated “to cast out.” As I said before, I chose Weymouth’s translation expel because it describes a familiar action of everyday life. Throughout this book I will use these expressions more or less interchangeably: cast out, drive out, expel.

Another Greek verb used in this connection is exorkizo, normally translated “to exorcise.” The kjv translates it “to adjure.” In contemporary English, to exorcise is defined as “to expel evil spirits from a person or a place by prayers, adjurations and religious rites.” The word is used frequently in the rituals of liturgical churches but occurs only once in the New Testament.

3

The Pattern and Mission of Jesus

When I was confronted publicly by the open defiance of a demon in a Sunday morning worship service (as I explained in chapter 1), I was impelled to study the New Testament accounts of how Jesus dealt with such things. He is the one and only foundation and pattern for all Christian ministry. In this chapter, therefore, I will examine in some detail how Jesus Himself dealt with demons.

One of the earliest scenes in His public ministry, in a synagogue in Capernaum, is described vividly in Mark 1:21-26:

Then they went into Capernaum, and immediately on the Sabbath He entered the synagogue and taught. And they were astonished at His teaching, for He taught them as one having authority, and not as the scribes. Now there was a man in their synagogue with an unclean spirit. And he cried out, saying, “Let us alone! What have we to do with You, Jesus of Nazareth? Did You come to destroy us? I know who You are – the Holy One of God!” But Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be quiet, and come out of him!” And when the unclean spirit had convulsed him and cried out with a loud voice, he came out of him.

The reaction of the people is described in verses 27 and 28:

Then they were all amazed, so that they questioned among themselves, saying, “What is this? A new doctrine with authority [margin]. He commands even the unclean spirits, and they obey Him.” And immediately His fame spread throughout all the region around Galilee.

In verse 23, when the nkjv says with an unclean spirit, the Greek actually says in an unclean spirit. Perhaps the nearest English equivalent would be under the influence of an unclean spirit.

It is noteworthy that the New International Version translates this phrase possessed by an evil spirit. This exemplifies how translations can mislead us regarding the activity of evil spirits (or demons). Nothing in the original Greek justifies the use of the word possessed, with its suggestion of ownership. This translation is an accommodation to traditional religious terminology that obscures the meaning of the original text.

Jesus had been preaching in Galilee, “The time is fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is at hand” (Mark 1:15). Now He had to demonstrate the superiority of His Kingdom over the kingdom of Satan. There are six important points to notice.

First, Jesus dealt with the demon, not with the man. The demon spoke out of the man, and Jesus spoke to the demon. Literally translated, what Jesus said to the demon was, “Be muzzled!”

Second, Jesus expelled the demon from the man, not the man from the synagogue.

Third, Jesus was in no way embarrassed by the interruption or disturbance. Dealing with the demon was part of His total ministry.

Fourth, the demon spoke in both singular and plural forms: “Did You come to destroy us? I know who You are. . .” (verse 24). This response is characteristic of a demon speaking for itself and on behalf of others. The demon in the man in Gadara used the same form of speech: “My name is Legion; for we are many” (Mark 5:9).

Fifth, it is reasonable to assume that the man was a regular member of the synagogue, but apparently no one knew he needed deliverance from a demon. Perhaps even the man himself did not know. The anointing of the Holy Spirit on Jesus forced the demon out into the open.

Sixth, it was this dramatic confrontation with a demon in the synagogue that launched Jesus into His public ministry. He became known to His fellow Jews first and foremost as the Man with unique authority over demons.

How Jesus Dealt with Demons

On the evening of the same day, when the people’s movements were no longer restricted by the Sabbath regulations, we might say that Jesus held His first “healing service”:

At evening, when the sun had set, they brought to Him all who were sick and those who were demon-possessed [demonized]. And the whole city was gathered together at the door. Then He healed many who were sick with various diseases, and cast out many demons; and He did not allow the demons to speak, because they knew Him.

Mark 1:32-34

The same events are described in Luke 4:40-41:

When the sun was setting, all those who had anyone sick with various diseases brought them to Him; and He laid His hands on every one of them and healed them. And demons also came out of many, crying out and saying, “You are the Christ, the Son of God!” And He, rebuking them, did not allow them to speak, for they knew that He was the Christ.

For a clear picture of how Jesus dealt with demons, we need to combine the two accounts of Mark and Luke. Mark says, “He did not allow the demons to speak,” but Luke says, “And demons also came out of many, crying out and saying, ‘You are the . . . Son of God!’” As in the incident in the synagogue, the demons declared their recognition of Jesus publicly as the Holy One of God, or the Son of God, but after that He allowed them to say nothing more.

It is noteworthy that people came to Jesus seeking healing for their sicknesses, but many of them had demons cast out of them. Apparently the people did not realise that some of their sicknesses were caused by demons. One remarkable characteristic of Jesus’ ministry, from beginning to end, is that He never made a hard and fast distinction between healing people’s sicknesses and delivering them from demons.

The same applies to His ongoing ministry of preaching, as described in Mark 1:39: “And He was preaching in their synagogues throughout all Galilee, and casting out demons.” Expelling demons was as normal a part of Jesus’ ministry as preaching. Delivering people from demons was both the confirmation and the practical application of the message He was preaching, which was: “The kingdom of God is at hand” (Mark 1:15).

To what kind of people, we might ask, was Jesus ministering in this way? Primarily observant Jews who met every Sabbath in the synagogue and spent the rest of the week caring for their families, tending their fields, fishing the sea and minding their shops. The people who received help from Jesus were mainly “normal,” respectable, religious people. Yet they were demonized. A demon had gained access to some area or areas of their personalities, and as a result they themselves were not in full control.

We need to remember that the moral and ethical code of Jewish people in Jesus’ time was based on the Ten Commandments and the Law of Moses. This meant that most of them were probably living better lives than the majority of people in our contemporary Western society.

Undoubtedly there are many similar people to be found in the Christian community today – good, respectable, religious people who attend church and use all the right religious language, yet are like the observant Jews of Jesus’ day. Some areas in their personalities have been invaded by demons and, as a result, they are not in full control. Surely they need deliverance just as much as the people to whom Jesus ministered!

In Luke 13:32 Jesus made it clear that His practical ministry to the sick and demonized was to continue unchanged to the end: “Behold, I cast out demons and perform cures today and tomorrow, and the third day I shall be perfected.” “Today, tomorrow and the third day” is a Hebraism that could be paraphrased, “From now on until the job is finished.” The practical ministry of Jesus began, continued and concluded with two activities: healing the sick and expelling demons. The way He began was the right way, and He never needed to improve on it.

Further, when the time came for Jesus to commission and send out disciples, He instructed them to continue in exactly the same pattern of ministry that He Himself had demonstrated. To the first twelve apostles He imparted a twofold authority: first, to expel demons; and second, to heal every kind of sickness and disease (see Matthew 10:1). Then He gave them explicit instructions as to how to use this authority: “And as you go, preach, saying, ‘The kingdom of heaven is at hand.’ Heal the sick, cleanse the lepers, raise the dead, cast out demons” (Matthew 10:7-8).

Mark gives a brief description of how the disciples carried out their task: “And they cast out many demons, and anointed with oil many who were sick, and healed them” (Mark 6:13). Casting out demons, then, was not an optional “extra”!

Later Jesus sent out seventy more disciples, in pairs, to prepare the way before Him in every place He intended to go. We do not have a detailed account of His instructions, but clearly it included casting out demons, for on the disciples’ return they reported with joy, “Lord, even the demons are subject to us in Your name” (Luke 10:17).

After His death and resurrection, Jesus again commissioned His disciples, but He now extended their ministry to the whole world. The message of those who went forth in faith and obedience, He promised, would be attested by five supernatural signs. The first two were these: “In My name they will cast out demons; they will speak with new tongues” (Mark 16:17).

Since the beginning of the twentieth century, a great deal has been preached, taught and written about the second sign: speaking with new tongues. But the sign Jesus put first, casting out demons, has not received the same positive attention. It is sad that the contemporary Western Church has been unwilling to come to grips with the issue of demons.

A further account of Jesus’ final commission to His disciples is given in Matthew 28:19-20:

“Go therefore and make disciples of all the nations, baptising them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, teaching them to observe all things that I have commanded you; and lo, I am with you always, even to the end of the age.”

This commission was simple and practical: to make disciples and then to teach them to obey all that Jesus had commanded the first disciples. Then these new disciples would in turn make further disciples, and teach them all that Jesus had taught. So it would go from one generation to another – “even to the end of the age.” Jesus started His disciples off with the right “programme” and never made any provision for it to be changed. Unfortunately, through the centuries the Church has made many unauthorised changes, none of them for the better!

The Pattern of New Testament Evangelism

The New Testament provides one clear example of a disciple who patterned himself on the ministry of Jesus: Philip. He is the only person in the New Testament specifically described as an “evangelist” (see Acts 21:8), and his ministry, described in Acts 8:5-13 and 26-40, is the pattern for New Testament evangelism.

Philip’s message was refreshingly simple. In Samaria it was “Christ.” To the Ethiopian eunuch it was “Jesus.” Philip needed no organising committee, no trained choir, no rented auditorium. The crowds gathered to hear him for one reason only: the dramatic demonstration of God’s supernatural power:

And the multitudes with one accord heeded the things spoken by Philip, hearing and seeing the miracles which he did. For unclean spirits, crying with a loud voice, came out of many who were possessed [demonized]; and many who were paralysed and lame were healed.

Acts 8:6-7

This is New Testament evangelism: The Gospel is preached and the multitudes hear; they see the miracles and casting out of demons and they believe; they are baptised and the Church is established. A central element is the expelling of demons, which is often accompanied by noisy and disorderly manifestations. Other features of evangelism vary, but this element is central to evangelism as practised in the New Testament, first by Jesus, then by His disciples.

The pattern of evangelism was not confined to the disciples who had been eyewitnesses of the ministry of Jesus. It was conspicuous in the ministry of the apostle Paul. At one point, in fact, Paul’s success in dealing with demons had an impact on the entire city of Ephesus:

God did extraordinary miracles through Paul, so that even handkerchiefs and aprons that had touched him were taken to the sick, and their illnesses were cured and the evil spirits left them.

Some Jews who went around driving out evil spirits tried to invoke the name of the Lord Jesus over those who were demon-possessed [demonized]. They would say, “In the name of Jesus, whom Paul preaches, I command you to come out.” Seven sons of Sceva, a Jewish chief priest, were doing this. One day the evil spirit answered them, “Jesus I know, and I know about Paul, but who are you?” Then the man who had the evil spirit jumped on them and overpowered them all. He gave them such a beating that they ran out of the house naked and bleeding.

When this became known to the Jews and Greeks living in Ephesus, they were all seized with fear, and the name of the Lord Jesus was held in high honour.

Acts 19:11-17, niv

Since these sons of Sceva were deliberately imitating Paul, they provide us with a “shadow” from which we can form a picture of how Paul dealt with demons. Apparently he spoke directly to them and commanded them in the name of Jesus to come out of their victims. In other words, Paul followed the pattern of Jesus Himself.

The ignominious failure of the sons of Sceva is also clear proof that success in casting out demons does not depend merely on using the right “formula.” The person using the formula must be a sincere and yielded channel for the supernatural Person of the Holy Spirit.

These events in Ephesus provide a further New Testament example of how the ministry of deliverance can affect an entire community. The spectacle of the sons of Sceva fleeing in disarray before a demonized man had an impact on the whole city of Ephesus, but especially on the Christians living there. It served to draw a clear dividing line between the disciples of Jesus and the unbelievers.

Many of those who believed now came and openly confessed their evil deeds. A number who had practised sorcery brought their scrolls together and burned them publicly. When they calculated the value of the scrolls, the total came to fifty thousand drachmas.

Acts 19:18-19, niv

Up to that time many of these believers had apparently been trying to live with one foot in the Kingdom of God and one in the kingdom of Satan. They had made a profession of faith in Christ but had retained in their possession scrolls containing the secret formulas they had used in their occult practices. Apparently these scrolls were very valuable, which may have been one reason the Christians were reluctant to part with them. But once their eyes were opened to the real spiritual issues, they were willing to watch their scrolls burn.

A drachma was one day’s wage. If we were to calculate the value of these scrolls in our own currency, basing it on forty dollars a day, the approximate minimum wage in the U.S., the equivalent would be more than two million dollars. Obviously there is money to be made in the occult!

The result of this dramatic confrontation between the two kingdoms is summed up in a closing verse: “So the word of the Lord grew mightily and prevailed” (Acts 19:20).

If evangelism is seldom conducted with these results in the Western world, we need to ask who has changed. Is it Jesus? Or the demons? Or the Church?

13

How Do Demons Come In?

For some time in the 1950s, I worked with a Christian medical specialist in London who had unusual insight into various areas of spiritual experience. He made one comment that has always stayed with me. “Remember,” he said, “the devil chooses the weakest moment and the weakest place.” I will apply this principle in seeking to answer the third question regarding the realm of the demonic: How do demons come in?

To attempt a comprehensive explanation of all the possible ways is far beyond the scope of this book. I will simply describe seven examples of moments or places of weakness through which demons habitually gain access to human personalities:

A family background in the occult or false religions
Other negative prenatal influences
Pressures in early childhood
Emotional shock or sustained emotional pressure
Sinful acts or habits
Laying on of hands
Idle words

Let us look at each of these areas of vulnerability.

1. A Family Background in the Occult or False Religions

In Exodus 20:3-5 the Lord warns of the evil consequences when people become involved in idolatry or false religion:

“You shall have no other gods before [or beside] Me.

“You shall not make for yourself any carved image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth; you shall not bow down to them nor serve them. For I, the Lord your God, am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children to the third and fourth generations of those who hate Me.”

God warns against all forms of idolatry or other involvement with false “gods.” The evil consequences of these particular sins can extend to four generations. Counting backward for four generations gives us four levels of ancestors:

Parents: 2

Grandparents: 4

Great-grandparents: 8

Great-great-grandparents: 16

Total: 30

Any or all of these thirty persons could be a channel through whom we may have been exposed to satanic influence. I doubt if any of us can guarantee that none of our thirty immediate ancestors was ever involved in any form of the occult or false religion.

This occult influence can begin while we are still in the womb. After all, what is weaker or more helpless than an unborn baby? It is entirely dependent on its parents for protection. Righteous, God-fearing parents provide that protection, but parents with an occult background expose their babies to the same spiritual influences that are at work in their own lives.

I have discovered that such babies are often demonized before they emerge from the womb. This is particularly true of people with backgrounds in Eastern religions such as Hinduism or Buddhism, or other false religions such as Freemasonry or Mormonism. In the next chapter I will deal more fully with the whole area of the occult.

2. Other Negative Prenatal Influences

Other negative forces may also affect an unborn child and expose it to demonic influence. A mother may resent or even hate the baby in her womb. Perhaps the mother is not married, or the father is unfaithful and irresponsible, or the mother may simply not want a child.

One thing a baby longs for, both before and after it is born, is love. When it does not feel love, it will probably begin to feel unwanted. This will in turn expose it to a deeper wound: rejection. Many babies are born with a spirit of rejection already in them.

At one time in the U.S. I encountered an unusually large number of people in a certain age group who suffered from rejection. When I checked their birth dates, I discovered that these fell between 1929 and 1934 – a time all older Americans remember as the Great Depression. I realised that mothers who were already having a hard time making ends meet resented the prospect of yet another mouth to feed. They may or may not have verbalised their resentment, but the sensitive little personalities in the womb felt it and came forth already carrying a spirit of rejection. This is just one of various demons that may affect an unborn child.

My own wife, Ruth, is a typical case. She was born in 1930, the eighth child in her family. Her parents were farmers who were struggling financially because of the Depression and the drought which caused that region of the U.S. to be labelled “the Dustbowl.” At age forty Ruth was saved and baptised in the Holy Spirit and in water. She was already in the Lord’s service when we married in 1978, yet she had an ongoing battle with rejection until the demon was identified and driven out. Even today she must be on her guard lest it assault her in a moment of weakness.

3. Pressures in Early Childhood

In James 3:16 we are warned, “Where envy and self-seeking exist, confusion and every evil thing are there.”

Broken, strife-torn homes, in which parents are in bitter conflict with each other and/or have little time for their children, provide an atmosphere that invites the presence and activity of demons. Most young children lack the necessary emotional and spiritual defences to withstand such demonic pressure. My personal observation (as I have said) is that most demonic problems begin in childhood.

In families in which the father has been an alcoholic, or cruel and dominating, or violent and abusive, girls often develop an intense hatred of men, which opens the door for the demon of hate. This is particularly true if the father has abused his daughters sexually. I have often speculated that this was the root cause of Esther’s problems (described in chapter 6). It would account for the powerful hold that the demon of hate had over her.

Other demons that commonly exploit such children are rejection, anger, fear, rebellion, misery, loneliness, depression and sometimes suicide. In the West there has been an alarming increase in the number of teenage suicides. In the U.S., from 1952 to 1992, the incidence of suicide among adolescents and young adults nearly tripled. In 1992 more teenagers and young adults died from suicide than from cancer, heart disease, AIDS, birth defects, strokes, pneumonia, influenza and chronic lung disease combined. In almost all these cases, according to my diagnosis, the demon of rejection opened the way for the demon of suicide.

4. Emotional Shock or Sustained Emotional Pressure

In 1 Peter 3:6 the apostle explains that Christian women may qualify as daughters of Sarah “if you do good and are not afraid with any terror.” The Greek word translated “terror” has a wide range of meanings. One lexicon describes it as “any vehement emotion; passionate excitement.” Another renders it either actively as “intimidation” or passively as “terror.”

Women often, but not always, have weaker emotional defences than men. They are especially subject to fear. One woman I prayed for told me that the spirit of fear had entered her when a frightening automobile accident took place right in front of her.

Today the vast coverage of the media means that millions around the world are exposed to sudden, shocking incidents. A brutal murder or a bus blown up or a building exploding may leave an indelible impression not only on the victims who survive, but on all the men, women and children who view the horror again and again on television.

Men as well as women are subject to many other forms of emotional pressure. Both men and women are subject, for example, to the passionate excitement of sexual desire. Sudden, unpremeditated yielding to such desire can often open the door to a spirit of lust. Indulging in sexual fantasies or watching pornography can have the same effect.

It sometimes happens, too, that a child or young person subjected to sexual assault may in that way unwittingly open up to a demon of lust. The demon has no respect for “innocence,” but simply uses this moment of weakness to force its way in. From that moment on, the child or young person is subjected to pressures of lust that are not the expression of anything in his or her character.

But it is not always a sudden surge of emotion that opens the way to a demon. It may be some persistent, unrelenting pressure. A man who through no fault of his own has to spend many weary months without employment may begin to brood over his inability to provide for his family. Discouragement may affect him in various ways. Some tactless remark by his wife or trivial disobedience by his children may provoke a sudden outburst and open the way for a demon of anger to slip in. Or the continuing pressure of enforced inactivity may open him up almost imperceptibly to a dark spirit of depression or hopelessness.

Similarly a woman whose husband continually belittles and criticises her may finally yield to a spirit of hopelessness. Or a mother seeking to protect her child from dangers that are often more imaginary than real may project a spirit of anxiety on the youngster, until the spirit forces its way in and takes up residence in the child.

Obviously there are many kinds of emotional shock or pressure to which people may be subjected. But these few examples may alert you to this form of demonic attack and help you build up your defences against it.

5. Sinful Acts or Habits

Sometimes a single decisive act may open the way to a demon. The decision of Judas Iscariot to betray Jesus was such an act. When he went out from the Last Supper with this intention, Luke records, “then Satan entered Judas” (Luke 22:3). Judas himself opened the door that he could not afterward close.

Actions much less heinous than that of Judas may open the way for a demon. My late friend Don Basham was once praying for a woman who needed deliverance from a spirit of lust. When Don commanded the demon to come out of her, it answered, “She invited me in!”

“When did she do that?” Don asked.

“When she went to that dirty sex movie,” the demon replied.

The woman had to repent and ask forgiveness for her sin before the demon could be compelled to leave her.

We need to remember that Satan is a legal expert. When some sinful act has opened the way for a demon, it will not leave until the sinful act has been confessed and cancelled by God’s forgiveness.

Any act of deliberate wrongdoing may open the way for a demon. Many such acts are possible – telling a premeditated lie, for instance, or shoplifting, or cheating on exams.

Again, it may not be a single act that opens the door. It may well be the deliberate, persistent practice of a sinful act that eventually becomes a habit. Secret sins like repeated masturbation or fornication or pornography almost inevitably open the way for demons. But other, more “respectable” habits can have a similar effect. Frequent overeating opens the way for a demon of gluttony. Persistent daydreaming opens the door to a spirit of fantasy. Habitual exaggeration in conversation opens the way for a lying spirit.

6. Laying On of Hands

Laying hands on a person in prayer is not just a picturesque religious ritual. It can be a powerful spiritual experience, a temporary interaction between two spirits through which supernatural power is released. Normally the power flows from the one laying on hands to the one on whom hands are laid, but at times it can flow the other way.

The power may do either good or evil. It may emanate from the Holy Spirit or from a demon, depending on the one from whom it flows. For this reason Paul established certain safeguards. “Do not lay hands on anyone hastily,” he wrote, “nor share in other people’s sins; keep yourself pure” (1 Timothy 5:22). In other words, be careful with whom you allow your spirit to interact!

The laying on of hands should be done reverently and prayerfully. Any person participating should make sure he or she is not thereby, in Paul’s words, sharing in another person’s sins.

It is a mistake to turn a group of people loose and encourage them to lay hands indiscriminately on one another. The following brief testimony from Ruth illustrates the danger:

In 1971 I was attending a charismatic meeting, and the speaker asked people to stand if they wanted prayer for healing. I had a bad cold, so I stood. He then instructed people seated nearby to lay their hands on us and pray for our healing. Four or five prayed for me.

When I awoke the next morning, my cold was better – but my fingers were all curled up and stiff and hurting. Immediately I thought, Someone with arthritis laid hands on me last night! I renounced the spirit of arthritis, and within five minutes all the symptoms were gone.

I was a very young believer, less than one year old, and I have been so grateful to God for teaching me then to be careful who lays hands on me.

7. Idle Words

This is an area in which many of us are caught off guard, yet one about which Jesus gave us some of His most solemn warnings.

“But I say to you that for every idle word men may speak, they will give account of it in the day of judgement. For by your words you will be justified, and by your words you will be condemned.”

Matthew 12:36-37

What are “idle words”? They are words we utter thoughtlessly, words that do not express our real thoughts or intentions. When we are called in question concerning such words, we often excuse ourselves by saying, “I didn’t really mean it,” or, “I was only joking,” as though this releases us from responsibility. Yet it is precisely these idle words that Jesus warns us against.

The fact that many Christians are habitually guilty of speaking idle words does not make it less serious. In fact, anyone who considers this warning of Jesus to be unimportant needs to repent.

Idle words can open the door to demons. In a fit of exasperation a person may say, “I’m sick and tired” of whatever it may be. He does not mean it literally, but he may be opening the door to a demon of sickness or tiredness. Words concerning death are particularly dangerous. Many times people say, “I nearly died laughing,” or, “You’ll die when you hear this one!” Death is a dark, evil power, and we are foolish to treat it lightly.

In a temporary fit of grief or discouragement, a person will often say, “I wish I were dead,” or, “I’d be better off dead.” Words like that are a direct invitation to the spirit of death. I have ministered to hundreds of people who opened themselves up to the spirit of death by such words carelessly spoken. (I will say more about the spirit of death in chapter 20.)

Making Jesus Lord

These seven examples illustrate some of the ways we and our children may be exposed to demonic influence. We need to remember, too, that demons are extremely persistent. A demon may be driven out but still seek to force its way in again. Jesus warned of this:

“When an unclean spirit goes out of a man, he goes through dry places, seeking rest, and finds none. Then he says, ‘I will return to my house from which I came.’ And when he comes, he finds it empty, swept, and put in order. Then he goes and takes with him seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter and dwell there; and the last state of that man is worse than the first. . . .”

Matthew 12:43-45

The unclean spirit returns to “his house” – that is, the person it formerly occupied – and it finds it “empty, swept, and put in order.” Then it takes “seven other spirits more wicked than himself,” re-enters the house with them and occupies it once again.

What was there about “the house” that opened the way for the demon to re-enter? The house was “swept” – that was no problem. It was “put in order” – that was no problem, either. But it was “empty” – that was the problem! The man had left his house vacant. He had never taken Jesus in to be his Lord.

When a person commits himself to Jesus as his Lord, he can look to Jesus for supernatural power to keep demons out. But without Jesus as Lord, he does not have the strength to protect his “house.” When the demon assaults him, it may quickly break down his ineffective resistance. Then, when the demon re-enters, it brings with it seven other demons, each more wicked than itself, and the person is worse off than he was before.

Let me illustrate with an example that became vivid to me. In the 1960s I generally travelled by car with Lydia to my preaching assignments in the U.S. Sometimes this meant a journey of two or three days. At evening, as we drove into a city, we would look for a neon sign with one word: Vacancy. When we saw that sign, we knew there was a motel open to receive us.

In the spiritual realm, Satan’s demons roam around looking for the same sign: Vacancy. When they see it, they say to themselves, Ah! Here’s a person who hasn’t made Jesus Lord of his life. Perhaps we’ll be able to force our way in. There is only one safeguard: making sure Jesus truly is Lord of every area of your life.

At the beginning of this chapter, I explained how a family background in the occult can open the way for demons. In the next chapter I will deal more fully with the whole area of the occult, emphasising the even greater danger of any form of direct, personal involvement.